Hello it's Scott Manley here.
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/dC2aCOaiGu0
原视频发布日期：20200708
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
你好 我是Scott Manley
Over the weekend Israel made a surprise launch of the Ofeq 16 satellite.
以色列上周末出人意料地发射了地平线16号卫星
This was launched onboard a Shavit-2 rocket and was billed as an earth observation satellite.
这是用沙维特2火箭发射的 被称为地球观测卫星
Really it's a military reconnaissance satellite.
其实它是一颗军事侦察卫星
Israel have been launching satellites on their own for quite a while.
以色列自己发射卫星已经有一段时间了
They actually started developing reconnaissance satellites.
他们其实早就开始研发侦察卫星了
More or less after the 1973 Yom Kippur War.
基本上是在1973年的赎罪日战争之后
Because US assets were not able to deliver the intelligence they wanted quickly enough for various reasons
在各种原因影响之下 他们想要的情报无法由美国的体系迅速地提供
so they developed their own launch system and they've been running this since but 1988
所以他们开发了自己的运载火箭 他们从1988年就开始使用这个火箭了
So this is the ninth successful launch of an Ofeq satellite.
所以这是地平线卫星的第九次成功发射
The last Ofeq satellite launched was or Ofeq 11 and that was launched in 2016
上一次发射的地平线卫星是地平线11 是在2016年发射的
We don't actually know what happened to Ofeq 12 to 15.
我们实际上不知道地平线12至15发生了什么
I suspect they might be part of some canceled design or they might be getting launched later.
我猜它们可能是被取消的设计 或者会在以后发射
I'm not really sure
我不太确定
Regardless. To satellite watchers that Ofeq satellites are kind of fascinating oddballs.
不管怎么说 对卫星爱好者来说 地平线卫星是一种迷人的奇葩
So like all things launched from Israel, they're launched by the Shavit rocket
就像所有从以色列发射的东西一样 它们由沙维特火箭发射
and they're launched into a retrograde orbit
并将其发射到逆行轨道
they're going the wrong direction around the earth.
它们绕着地球的方向走错了
So all of the spacecraft launched by Israel have an orbit.
所以以色列发射的所有航天器都有一个轨道
There's roughly a 142 degrees of inclination
大概有142度的倾角
which means they're sort of going west or east to west rather than west to east.
这意味着这是自东向西 而不是自西向东
And yeah this is highly unusual in space launch
是的 这在太空发射中是非常不寻常的
because of course going west to east you pick up the velocity of the earth
当然是因为自西向东你会获得地球自转的速度
but they need to do this because it's a requirement
但以色列不得不这样做
that they don't drop spent rocket stages on any of their neighbors to the east
他们不会把火箭残骸扔到东边的任何一个邻国身上
They have Jordan. They have Saudi Arabia.
他们有约旦 沙特阿拉伯
Various other nations to the east which are which might have not be happy if they drop something on them.
如果以色列向他们扔东西 他们可能会不高兴
Alternatively, Israel may not want these nations to be examining the spent rocket hardware
或者说 以色列可能不希望这些国家检查火箭残骸
and that is another reason why they choose to launch over the Mediterranean.
这也是他们选择在地中海上空发射的另一个原因
So all the launches occur from Palmachim Airbase and then they head west out over the Mediterranean Sea
所以 所有的发射都是从帕尔马奇姆空军基地出发 然后向西飞越地中海
and it's believed if the rocket were able to launch eastwards they would more than double their payload capacity
如果火箭能够向东发射 相信他们的有效载荷能力会增加一倍以上
but even going west they're actually very careful with their launch trajectories.
但即便是往西走 他们的发射轨迹其实也是非常谨慎的
The kind of tried to stay over the Mediterranean as much as possible
是尽量停留在地中海上空的那种
practically aiming to thread the needle over the Straits of Gibraltar
就像是要把针从直布罗陀海峡上空穿过去
that means they're carefully sliding between Europe and Africa
这意味着他们要小心翼翼地在欧洲和非洲之间滑动
so the Shavit rockets are built by the Israel Aerospace Industries
所以沙维特火箭是由以色列航空工业公司制造的
and the current version of this is the Shavit 2
而目前的版本是沙维特2
and it's an evolution obviously of the original Shavit which launched back in 1988.
而它显然是1988年发射的原始沙维特火箭的改进版
The design is an all solid rocket motor design.
该火箭使用全固体火箭发动机的设计
It uses three solid rocket stages.
它使用三个固体火箭级
The first two stages are practically identical.
前两级实际上是相同的
They're the same mass, the same diameter in the same length.
质量相同 直径相同 长度相同
But the second stage has a larger vacuum optimized nozzle.
但第二级有一个更大的真空优化喷嘴
So on the original Shavit the stages are 1.3 meters in diameter and 6.4 meters long and the mass is about 10 tons.
所以在原来的沙维特上 两级的直径是1.3米 长度是6.4米 质量是10吨左右
Slightly different because of the different nozzle sizes.
因为喷嘴大小不同 所以推力略有不同
Both these stages burn for 52 seconds and the first stage will generate 46 tons of thrust.
这两级分别点火52秒 第一级会产生46吨的推力
In the second thrust the second stage gets 48 tons of thrust thanks to that larger nozzle.
在第二级推力中 由于那个更大的喷管 第二级会得到48吨的推力
Now the third stage is much smaller.
那么第三级就小多了
It's only 2.6 meters long and it's a big 2.6 tons.
它只有2.6米长 而且是2.6吨的重
It'll generate 6.2 tons of thrust for 90 seconds.
它将在90秒内产生6.2吨的推力
Unlike the previous stages this doesn't have any steering capability or any thrust vectoring.
与前几级不同的是 它没有任何转向能力 也没有任何推力矢量
It's spin stabilized.
它是自旋稳定的
So during the launch the first two stages fire and accelerate the rocket up onto a ballistic trajectory.
所以在发射过程中 前两级通过点火加速 将火箭送到弹道轨迹上
And they'll typically burn out at around 100 kilometers
它们通常会在100公里左右关机
when the vehicle will continue upwards to reach about 250 kilometers.
之后 飞行器将继续向上达到250公里左右
During the cruise up to that apogee altitude, there is an equipment section on the top,
在巡航到该远地点高度的过程中 顶部有一个设备舱段
there which will it basically encompasses the second stage
差不多就是盖住二级的位置
and you can actually see this in the video that was released.
实际上你会在这个发布出来的视频里看到它
it points this in the correct orientation and then spins up the upper-stage before a letting go.
它会指向正确的方向 然后在分离之前旋转上面级
Then when that upper stage finally fires its spin stabilized and the spacecraft is put into the correct orbit.
然后当上级最终点火的时候 它就自旋稳定了 航天器就被放到了正确的轨道上
So the Shavit 1 or the Shavit's design was used to launch the first two satellites Ofeq 1 and 2.
所以沙维特1或者沙维特的设计被用来发射了前两颗卫星地平线1和2
Those had masses of about 160 kilograms and then they introduced an upgrade, the Shavit 1.
这两颗卫星的质量大约为160公斤 然后他们推出了升级版沙维特1
They just stretched that first stage to 7.5 meters long.
他们把第一级的长度加长到7.5米
That's an extra meter long.
也就是比原先长了一米
They also made it wider by five centimeters one point three five meters in total.
他们还把它加宽了5cm 总共加宽到1.35m
So that raised the total mass to 14 tons and the thrust was up to 62 tons.
这样一来 总质量就增加到了14吨 推力也达到了62吨
And this was used for four launches Ofeq three through six from 1995 to 2004.
从1995年到2004年 地平线3到6号共进行了四次发射
But two of these launches were unsuccessful.
但其中有两次发射不成功
Those satellites were significantly heavier.
这些卫星明显更重
But you know the final version that flew over the weekend is the Shavit 2 that debuted in 2007.
但你知道上周末发射的最终版本是2007年首次亮相的沙维特2号
And all they did was they took that stretched first stage
他们所做的一切就是把那个拉长的一级
and they made the second stage use that stretched model as well.
也放到二级上去了
So you can tell the difference or which design of Shavit rocket is
所以你可以分辨出沙维特火箭的区别
using by looking for where the ridge is where the rocket changes diameter.
通过寻找火箭的收敛段位置来判断
So yeah the Shavit 2 has been able to launch 260 kilogram spacecraft by the sound of things.
所以是的 沙维特2号已经能够发射260公斤的航天器 听起来是这样的
And yeah that's what they're flying these days.
是的 这也是他们最近发射的载荷
Now the design of the Shavit rocket actually goes back to Israel's ICBM project called Jericho.
沙维特火箭的设计可以追溯到 以色列的杰里科 洲际弹道导弹项目
That began in the 1960s and the primary development was originally carried out by Dassault Aviation in France.
该项目开始于20世纪60年代 最初由法国达索公司进行研发
The first and second stages of the Shavit are literally taken directly from the Jericho 2 missile.
沙维特的第一级和第二级简直是直接取自杰里科2导弹
In fact most of what we know about the performance of the Jericho missiles
事实上 我们所知道的关于杰里科导弹的大部分性能
are derived from the performance of the Shavit launch vehicle.
是源于沙维特运载火箭的性能
The design incidentally was also licensed to South Africa
顺便说一句 该设计还被授权给南非
and they produced a series of missiles and rockets called the RSA series.
让他们生产了一系列的导弹和火箭 称为RSA系列
These were ballistic missiles.
这些都是弹道导弹
They also worked on building a launch vehicle
他们还致力于制造一种运载火箭
and they actually had three suborbital launches which were carried out in 1989 and 1990.
实际上这种火箭分别在1989年和1990年进行过三次亚轨道发射
But before they reached orbit the program was cancelled in 1994.
但在火箭入轨之前 在1994年 该计划被取消
There was one other spin-off where there was an attempt to commercialize the project.
还有一个衍生项目试图将其商业化
That was a partnership between IAI and Astrium and that began in 2001.
那是IAI(以色列航空工业公司)和阿斯特里姆(空客子公司)之间的合作 始于2001年
They incorporated, set it up, started advertising it.
他们注册了公司 成立了公司 开始做广告
Curiously because of US government rules on launch vehicles.
奇怪的是 由于美国政府对运载火箭的规定
They ended up deciding to essentially build a copy of Shavit in the US using US hardware.
他们最后决定基本上是用美国的硬件在美国建造一个沙维特的副本
So one design had a file called Castor 120 motor as the first and second stages.
所以某个文件中透露出的设计是 使用Castor 120作为一级和二级的发动机
And then the third stage would be a file called Star 48.
有兴趣可以去看看Charon_S丶的Star系列固体火箭发动机大全上cv6559432和下cv6629275
三级则是使用Star 48上面级
And uh actually the commercial versions all added this a monopropellant hydrazine engine on the top
而实际上 商业版本都在顶部增加了一个单组元推进剂的肼发动机
so they could what that would actually help with their orbit trim and orbit insertion accuracy.
所以 这将有助于进行轨道修正和提高轨道进入精度
I'm pretty sure.
这我很确定
But yeah this thing was apparently incorporated in 2001 and I haven't seen any updates on it
但这东西显然是在2001年被公布的 我没有看到在这之后任何更新的信息
so I'm gonna presume that that whole project is dead.
如同科学家认为没好果汁吃的已经凉了的木卫四一样 av243791309 01:55
所以我认为整个项目已经凉了
Also something keeps coming back is the idea of air launching the Shavit
另外 有件事我一直在想 那就是空中发射沙维特的想法
and you know air launch has limited gains we've also obviously mentioned this before
而且你知道空中发射的收益有限 我们之前也很明显地提到了这一点
but the Shavit actually stands to gain a lot if it was air launched.
但如果是空射的话 沙维特实际上会有很大的收益
Because as we points to it normally launches westwards over the Mediterranean
因为正如我们所指出的 它通常在地中海上空向西发射
but if you could put it on say a Boeing 747 or Hercules
但如果你能把它放在波音747或大力神上的话
if they could be carried out of Israel down through the Red Sea and over into the Indian Ocean
如果他们能被带出以色列 穿过红海 进入印度洋
and then they could launch eastwards and they could take advantage of the rotation of the earth.
然后他们可以向东发射 他们可以利用地球的自转
They could get a significant boost front from that and it would get a boost from being air launched.
它们可以从地球自转和空射中获得显著的助推力
So that actually makes a lot more sense but I'm not sure that's gonna happen either.
所以这实际上更有意义 但我也不确定这是否会发生
So summing up the Shafiq is a curious launch vehicle for many reasons.
所以总结起来 各种方面来看 沙维特都是一个奇怪的运载火箭
Partly the history, partly the reasons behind it working.
一部分是历史 一部分是它发射过程背后的各种原因
And you know honestly it doesn't actually make very much sense as a launch vehicle for anyone
而且说实话 对任何人来讲这个火箭都不太合理
except the Israeli military whose secrecy is very important to their payloads
除了以色列军方 因为对于他们的有效载荷而言 保密非常重要
and at that point it makes just enough sense to exist.
而这一点就足够支撑它存在下去
But for heavier payloads that don't need that level of secrecy,
锁眼和导师有话说
但对于更重的有效载荷 不需要这种程度的保密性
they can actually buy launch services from other providers which have well the better situated launch sites.
以色列实际上可以从其他供应商那里购买发射服务 而这些供应商有更好的发射场
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全